Docker Commands

1. Docker pull image_name:tag => To pull image from docker hub

2. Docker images => List of images 

3. Docker run image_name:tag => Run container based on the image, we can have multiple containers for same image

Docker run -d image_name:tag => Run container in background
Too see logs, docker logs container_id (container_id can be fetched from docker ps command)

4. Docker ps => List of running containers with meta information

5. Docker stop container_id => Stop docker container

Port Binding - Containers running on an IP which can be called from our local machine

standard to use same host port as of container port

6. Docker run -d -p Host_port:Container_port image_name:tag 

Host port can be our unused port
Container_port (can be found through docker ps command)

7. Docker ps -a => Shows all the open and exited/closed containers 

You can see the list and then rerun a previously closed container



—————————
Kubernetes

A Kubernetes cluster is a group of nodes that run containerized applications.
(Control Plane, worker nodes and pods)

Node => A node is a physical or virtual machine that runs pods in a Kubernetes cluster.

Components -> Pods/Service/Ingres

Pod -> An abstraction layer on top of a container
Usually one application per pod
Each pod has its own IP address
New IP Address on recreation(pods can be killed because of resource issue or application crash)

Therefore IP address of pods is dynamic

Service => Permanent IP address and different lifecycle that of a pod. 
Used to communicate between 2 pods

Could be of External(exposed to outer world) or Internal Type(ex Database)

Service has IP address rather than domain name and secure protocols. 

Hence requests first come to Ingres(which has domain and protocols) and Ingres route the request to the respected IP internally

ConfigMap and Secret

Kubernetes has config map for external configurations such as database url(which may change) and also has Secret component to store for ex database Id pwd

We can use config map and secrets as environment variables or properties file in a pod

Volume

Kubernetes Cluster doesn’t have any data persistence.
The storage we are talking is storing the data which is generated by a pod, since pods can be killed easily we need a storage.

 Hence we can have internal or external storage. Internal Storage means storage on the node on which pod is running and external meaning storage on a disk outside node.

Deployments and Blueprint of pods

Replicate everything on multiple nodes(servers).

All replica’s will be connected to same Service (in order to have constant domain name across).
Service also acts as a load balancer for the pods(sends request to least busy pod)

Deployment is a component which is basically an abstraction of pods.

If a pod dies then Service forwards request to another pod.

StatefulSet
Since databases has state of data, if a database instance is killed then we cannot direct requests to another database instance as they both needs to be consistent.

Note: Deployment Component is for stateless apps
StatefulSet is for stateful apps or database.

It is challenging to manage state in Kubernetes hence it is said to deploy only stateless apps in kubernetes. Databases should be deployed externally.

Kubernetes Configuration

All configurations to kubernetes cluster goes through a master node called API server.

The clients for this API server to talk to kubernetes are UI(k8 dashboard), API’s(script or curl command), CLI(kubectl).

Through these clients we have only one main entry point to make request for the kuberenetes configurations (how many replications, namespaces, regions, secrets, environments etc).

These requests are either in yaml format or json format.

There are 3 parts to configuration in k8(metadata ex replicas, specification and status(added by k8))

The status is always compared with metadata by etcd component (Control Plane has Api Server, Scheduler, Controller manager and etcd). The status tells the current status of pods (how many are alive) and based on this status it compares with the metadata we provided. It uses Key Value database to manage this.

Kubectl is used to interact with any Kuberenetes Cluster.